[Music]
hello everyone welcome to another
episode of the of pitch where we cover
views and operations that might be
interesting to operate with the now in
this episode we'll be explaining how
usada and the athletic Integrity unit or
AIU work together to optimize testing
for track and field athletes we'll talk
about the frequency timing and
processing designment I'm joined today
by two subject matter experts on this
topic Laura the director of science at
usada and Tomar the head of pesting
science at AIU welcome Laura and
Tomar thanks Avery it's always great to
be back on the
pitch hi every uh nice to be here for
the first time thank you both so let's
dive in what's the biggest benefit of
the close collaboration between usada
and
AIU yeah Avery so obviously sport is
global and we realize that athletes are
you know training and competing all over
the world so for usid this means that
our us athletes might travel overseas to
for training camps and competitions and
this can be quite logistically
challenging for us to test and similarly
the AIU is responsible for a global
testing pool of athletes obviously not
just the us and that means a lot of
athletes in a lot of places yeah and and
um and I would add that in addition um
no surprise here but you USA is a is a
is a a key country for track and field
it's one of the most successful if not
the number one country in the world so
it's it's really important for us to be
able to rely on a solid partner like you
um uh in in in such important country so
um and and the first reason is because
this partnership allows us to cover a
broad pool of
athletes um the important what we try to
achieve with USI is to make sure that
the national team competing at the major
events I'm talking about wch Olympic
games are adequately tested and uh our
collaboration with us allows us to cover
a large pool of athletes in the USA
which is really important I mean USA is
usually the biggest team at major events
and having this partnership allows us to
cover a really large pool um and uh it's
all the more important in the US that
there's a high density of top Elite
athletes especially in like springs for
example in a lot of disciplines um and
there's a trial system so there's an
uncertainty as to who is finally is
going to make the team uh so having this
large program in combin com combining
aru program and USA program allows us to
cover this large pool in the end to test
a vast majority of athletes and besides
there's a a growing number of uh Elite
foreign athletes competing on the US
soil uh and for example in on the NCA
circuit um and and actually USA is
assisting us testing those foreign
athletes in the USA um and this is this
is great I mean this is one of the um us
has this capacity is one of the only
country in the world that has this
capacity yeah I agree uh tomasa the
biggest benefit I guess for us is for
our collaboration is really being able
to pull our testing resources to ensure
that both the US athletes and the
foreign athletes so the training and
competing in the US are held to that
same high standard of testing to
ultimately promote clean Sport and how
do you make sure resources that wasted
and that and AIU testing doesn't over
and like I think that's proba one of the
the top questions that folks are going
to want to know about you yeah good
question Avery on a really regular basis
both our respective science B and
testing teams get together and really
try and optimize our testing strategy so
we're trying to you know be as strategic
and efficient with our testing resources
as possible and you know that's
basically not simply avoiding each other
with testing we're actually trying to be
intentional with with our plans um and
that usada we also hope that if we can
kind of carry some of that testing load
in the US um you know being such a large
Federation as toas said that would allow
the AIU to focus maybe more of their
testing resources on smaller countries
that don't have that same level of nto
support or funding
yeah Laur that's a very important point
for the AIU and that's something that um
people should you know should should
understand this uh this partnership and
the trust the mutual trust we have with
usada allows us to use our resources for
other countries that need more attention
um we we have over 100 nationalities on
the a testing testing program which is a
truly Global program track and field is
a universal sport um and um
unfortunately there are still major
discrepancies between uh National
Domestic antidoping programs um and and
having this strong program in the USA
allows us to focus our resources on
other countries with no or very limited
uh testing
programs um and for elite athletes who
may be challenging USS athletes at major
events so there's a gap and it's our
role as um International fation to fill
that Gap uh but we only fill the gap
because there's a strong program in the
USA um but it's important for we think
it's important for us athletes to know
that absolutely can athletes expect to
see differences uh in the dcos for
AI yeah of course uh even with a usada
test athletes shouldn't expect the same
dco to be coming um each time although
of course the longer you're in the sport
I'm sure you're going to start to
recognize some of the same
dcos and I for the the test that the AIU
conducts they have the choice so they
can partner with usada in which case a
usada dco will likely come who may or
may not be familiar to the athlete uh
but they can also choose to use a third
party collection agency in which case it
would be a non-used
EO although we I mean as as Laura said
we usually use um uh us and and and for
our own testing so there will be us dcos
doing our testing but also we try to
keep a a proportion of independent
testing within our program um so that
you know um there are all different
phases um it's important for us to keep
this independent proportion but in the
end of the day the the as Laur said the
the sample collection uh procedure is
pretty standardized uh so there
shouldn't be significant differences in
the way uh tests are collected and um uh
the the dcus we use are from private
service companies which are operating in
the US um and we asked them to change
the dcos you know on a regular basis so
that to prevent the too much familiarity
between uh dcos and athletes it has some
good sides but we we you know uh we want
to avoid uh keep keep some distance um
with the athletes while still being
friendly and and nice and
professional yeah to so I guess to
summarize that uh because it can be you
know bit complicated with a multitude of
different combinations of who could come
and test but you know you could
essentially be tested by usada with the
usada
dco by the International Federation so
in this case the Athletics Integrity
unit with the us dco or it could be the
International Federation with a non us
dco a third party um dco and as Tamar
said everyone needs to follow the
international standard of testing so
all the collections need to follow
strict protocols and procedures which
are designed to protect the athletes
rights so if you ever have any concerns
make sure you note it on the doping
control form at the time of sample
collection but also you know please
reach out to the AIU or us with those
concerns def all right that's a wrap for
today come on Laura thank you so much
again for your time today thanks a
always a pleasure thanks the opportunity
thanks a
[Music]
lot